2)	Relational Queries

	2.1)	Write a query, using TUPLE CALCULUS, to print the drinkers that frequent only bars that serves some beer that they like (assume each drinker likes at least one beer and frequents at least one bar)


			{P | ∃L1 ∈ LIKES ∃L2 ∈ LIKES ∃S ∈ SERVES(L1.drinker='John' ^ S.beer = L1.beer ^ L2.drinker = 'Michael' ^ L1.beer != L2. beer ^ P.bar = S.bar)}

	
	2.2)	Write a query, using RELATIONAL ALGEBRA, to print the drinkers that frequent only bars that serves some beer that they like (assume each drinker likes at least one beer and frequents at least one bar).


			SELECT DISTINCT D.name, D.addr
    				FROM Drinkers AS D, Frequents AS F, Likes AS L, Sells AS S
     				WHERE D.name = L.drinker AND
          				D.name = F.drinker AND
	  				S.beer = L.beer AND
	  				S.bar = F.bar AND
	  				S.bar = 'Buckley''s Bar'


			SELECT DISTINCT D.name, D.addr
    				FROM Drinkers AS D,
         				((Frequents NATURAL JOIN Likes) NATURAL JOIN Sells) AS F
    				WHERE D.name = F.drinker AND
          				F.bar = 'Buckley''s Bar'


			JohnLikes(beer) := PI_{beer}(SIGMA_{drinker = 'John'}(Beers JOIN Likes))
			NotJohnLikes(beer) := PI_{beer}(Sells) - JohnLikes 
			Ans(bar) := PI_{bar}(Sells) - PI_{bar}(Sells JOIN NotJohnLikes) 


3)	Query Processing.

	3.1)	Describe tradeoffs that you would consider in selecting one of the algorithms.


			A nested loops join is particularly effective if the outer input is small and the inner input is preindexed and large. In small, such as those affecting only a small set of rows, index nested loops joins are superior to both merge joins and hash joins. In large queries, however, nested loops joins are often not the optimal choice.

			Merge join itself is very fast, but it can be an expensive choice if sort operations are required. However, if the data volume is large and the desired data can be obtained presorted from existing B-tree indexes, merge join is often the fastest available join algorithm.



	3.2)	What are the major costs and performance factors associated with each algorithm.


			Hash join provides excellent performance for equality joins, and can be tuned to require very few extra disk accesses beyond a one-time scan, which, provided enough memory is available. However, hash join is worthless for non-equality joins. 

			Sort-merge joins are suitable when there is either an equality or non-equality based join condition. Sort-merge also leaves the results sorted which is often a desired property. Sort-merge join has extra costs when you have to use external sorting, which, there is not enough memory to do the sort in-memory. 

			Nested-loop joins, which is already the worst type of join a db can execute and may be dozens of times slower in app-side code versus in the db engine, due to the extra network traffic involved

	
	3.3)	Under what circumstances, in general would you use each technique?


			Hash joins are used when the joining large tables.

			Sort merge join is used to join two independent data sources.

			Nested Loops would be used when the outer loop is formed which consists of few entries and then for each entry, and inner loop is processed.


	3.4)	Give an example of asituation in which you would select each of the algorithms, ie. charactistics of the database and query.

			Hash Join:
				Used when merging companies need to merge their databases into a single database

			Sort Merge:
				Used when you need to divide the dataset into two portions and applying merge sort on each half using a recursive technique.

			Nested Loop:
				Used when you read rows from the first table in a loop one at a time, passing each row to a nested loop that processes the next table in the join.